# 大家好 今天那個小狗
Hi everyone! The doggy,
# 那個母狗哇 下 下崽啦
I mean the mother, gave, gave birth today.
# 我去市場買了一條那麼大的魚
I've bought such a big fish from the market.
# 給它做
I'll make her,
# 給它做月子餐
I'll make her a postpartum meal.
# 我洗一下
Let me wash it.
# 這麼大的魚 我直接放到鍋里面
Such a big fish. I'll just put it into the wok,
# 直接炸
and fry it right away.
# 來來來
Come, come, come!
# 吃
Eat it!
# 它不要 給不吃
It doesn't want it. You have it.
# 小狗要
Yes, the puppy wants it!
# 要嗎
Does it?
# 我把火打開
Let me start the fire.
# 這個沒開
This is not switched on.
# 加點油下去
Put some oil.
# 沒由肯定不好吃
It can't taste good without oil.
# 你看 這個狗多幸福哇
Look! What a blessing for the dog,
# 生在我們家
to be born in our family.
# 買了那麼大一條魚給它吃
I bought her such a big fish.
# 豬肉貴
Pork is too expansive.
# 這個買魚
That's why I bought fish.
# 魚的營養也不錯的哦
Fish is also rather nutritious, in fact.
# 加點鹽下去
Put some salt.
# 死魚翻身 (註︰找不到一句貼切的了，所以直接意譯算)
Turn it over.
# 翻不過來喲
It doesn't work.
# 大啦
Big,
# 這條魚買了太大啦
the fish is just too big.
# 又怕那狗吃不飽 所以買了一條那麼大的魚
I wanna make sure that the dog has enough to eat. That's why I've bought such a big fish.
# 好香啊
It smells good!
# 這個 這是正宗的草魚喲
This is, this is an authentic grass carps.
# 這農戶 農戶養的
It's raised, raised by the farmers.
# 我們沒捨得吃
Not even us can have such a chance to have this fish.
# 給狗吃啊
But I give it to the dog.
# 它比較辛苦一點
Life is tough for her.
# 好啦 這個 魚湯煮好啦
Alright! The fish soup is done.
# 你看 整條哦 整條魚
Look! The whole, the whole fish,
# 煮得稀巴爛
is completed softened.
# 骨頭 這個骨頭
Bones, the bones
# 等下冷啦 我就給它吃
I'll give it to her when it's cooled down.
# 要先等一下
Leave it for a while.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個魚湯做好啦 好香哦
The fish soup is done. It smells so good!
# 你們吃飽了啊 你們就不用啦
You've eaten enough, haven't you? So you don't need it.
# 端到那母狗吃
I'm taking it to the mother.
# 那麼多狗
So many dogs!
# 你不要爬上來
Don't come with me!
# 這些狗
These dogs...
# 把門關緊
Shut the door.
# 狗
Dog!
# 來 吃個大餐
C'mon! Have a big feast!
# 你看 這狗
Look! This dog,
# 很矯情哦
is spoiled.
# 要我送到它面前來
She doesn't even move a bit, until I,
# 它才來
put it right in front of her.
# 看一下它的寶寶
Have a look at her babies.
# 嗯嗯
Hum hum!
# 哎呀 難怪它吃得那麼香 這個
Aya! That's why it's eating so merrily, this puppy.
# 這個跟竹鼠那麼小一點 (註︰竹鼠那麼小一點...我要把它譯出來)
This is as small as a bamboo rat,
# 很小
very small.
# 這個 真的六七兩 這個有
It's, really like, not more than 350 grams.
# 這次 這窩下得比較少
This time, there are fewer in this litter.
# 它的腳受傷啦
Her leg is injured.
# 腳受傷啦 下了4個
Her leg is injured. She has four babies.
# 我一個一個檢查一下
Let me check one by one.
# 公的
A boy
# 小狗 小 小 小狗崽很健康
The puppies, pup, pup, puppies are very healthy.
# 想喝奶是不是
You want some milk, don't you?
# 等你媽媽吃掉這條魚
You will have plenty of milk,
# 就有很多奶吃啦
when your mom has finished this fish.
# 那麼大 力氣都好大
It's very strong, though it's so small.
# 誒 多少條公的
Eh? How many boys?
# 條兩條都是公的哦
These two are both boys.
# 三條都是公的
Three are boys.
# 就一條母的 3條公的
Just one girl, the other three are boys.
# 呵呵
Ho ho
# 這條母狗很聽話的
She's a very good girl,
# 最聽話的就是它
the best dog in our family.
# 其它都是好調皮
Others are all very naughty.
# 來 再看一下你
Come! Let me take a look again.
# 小狗
Puppy!
# 你看 很漂亮哦 就昨天晚上生的
Look! It's pretty! They were born just last night.
# 狗頭
Dog head
# 小狗
Puppy!
# 歡迎你來到這個世界
Welcome to this world!
# 它牙齒都還沒有
It doesn't even have teeth.
# 這個世界很美好哦
It's a beautiful world, you know.
# 嗯 這個
Um! This one.
# 慢點吃
No rush!
# 看 這個狗都很乖的
Look! This puppy is really nice.
# 小狗
Puppy!
# 來呀 你的舌頭好漂亮
C'mon! You have a pretty tongue!
# 來呀 來來來 再舔一下
C'mon! Come, come come! Lick again!
# 吃得好跑哇 肚子都圓溜溜的
It's very well fed. Its belly is big and round.
# 生上來就會吃奶
Milk sucking is an innate instinct.
# 這麼奇怪
Amazing!
# 它會叫的哦
It yelps.
# 哦
Oh!
# 長大了很[SIC]定很兇 它這個
It must be very fierce when it's grown up, this puppy.
# 現在我們把門關起來呀 讓那個小狗
We close the door now, to let the puppies,
# 讓那個大狗哇 一直吃 吃飽來
let the big dog, just eat, until she's full.
# 我們上去把那個小豬放出來
Let's go up to get the piggy out,
# 放一條小豬下來
get a piggy down here,
# 那條最胖的
the fattest one.
# 不放出來等一下它都是變憂鬱啦
It will be depressed if I don't get it out.
# 沒人跟它玩
Cuz it has nobody to play with.
# 我來搞出來
I'll get it out.
# 叫老弟他們幫忙 直接把它抓出來
We ask our younger brothers to help. We'll just grab it out.
# 那麼多狗
So many dogs!
# 那麼小 等一下豬踩你一腳你就知道啦
You're so tiny. You'll certainly regret when the pigs step on you.
# 快走 快點走
Go, go, go! Hurry up!
# 把它放出來
Let it go out!
# 那小豬肯定又胖啦
The piggy must have grown fatter again.
# 抱都抱不動啦
I just can't hold it.
# 好動啊 現在
It's so heavy now.
# 差不多60斤啦
It's almost 30 kilograms.
# 現在跑到樹 樹 樹林裡面去啦
It runs in, in, into the woods now.
# 它不敢出來
It's too scared to come out.
# 你看 那條小豬
Look! That piggy,
# 它在偷吃那個酒糟哦
It's stealing the distillers grains.
# 等多吃一點它就暈啦
It will get dizzy if it eats too much.
# 我把它放出來吃酒糟 它以為我們把它幹嘛嘞
I get it out to let it eat the distillers grains. But it thought that we wanted to do something else.
# 它以為我們把它幹嘛啦 叫得那麼慘
It thought that we wanted to do something else, and was screaming so miserably.
# 現在多享受啊 趴在那裡
It enjoys it so much now. It's lying there,
# 慢慢享受
enjoying the distillers grains.
# 等一下它馬上就醉啦
It will get drunk soon.
# 等它醉了的時候 我們就把它抬下去
We'll take it down there when it gets drunk.
# 把這條豬灌醉
Juice up the pig.
# 吃飽一點啊
Eat more!
# 吃了等一下你就醉啦
You'll get drunk very soon.
# 小豬 好不好吃
Piggy! Does it taste good?
# 吃得爽歪歪喲
It's eating so merrily.
# 理都不理我 沒事
It doesn't even care about me.
# 沒事
No worries!
# 它害怕
It's scared.
# 你看 這個豬
Look! The pig,
# 它還想吃哦
it still wants to eat.
# 還沒吃過癮
It's still wants more.
# 還想過來
It wants to come again.
# 小豬 過來一齊吃啊
Piggy! Let's eat together!
# 它不敢
It's too scared.
# 我要走開一點 它才能 它才敢來
I need to move away a bit. Then it dares, dares to come.
# 你看 那些都沒有吃
Look! They don't even have their shares.
# 都是眼睜睜的看著它吃
They can just helplessly watch it eating.
# 你看 多幸福哇
Look! It's so privileged.
# 不能再吃啦 再吃它就醉啦
That's all for it. It will get drunk otherwise.
# 我把它放進去
Let me throw it in.
# 來 給你們好吃啦
C'mon. I have something good for you!
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 翻掉啦
It flipped over.
# 管它
Well, anyway
# 你看 這
Look! The,
# 這個豬 吃得好歡啊
the pigs are eating so merrily.
# 這條母豬也快生啦 看到沒有
The sow is about to give birth, see?
# 你看 外面這條豬
Look! This pig outside,
# 它還想進去吃哦
it still wants to come in and eat.
# 那條吃得有點多
It has eaten a bit too much.
# 好像有點暈暈的 呵
It seems a bit tipsy, ho!
# 等一下你們全部都喝醉
You'll all get drunk.
# 這條公豬暈啦 我就把它閹啦
I'll have the boar castrated if it gets drunk.
# 沒效果啊
It's not working.
# 這個酒糟對它好像沒甚麼效果
The distillers grains don't seem to have any effect on it.
# 這裡有兩 3條公豬哇 包括這條
Here are two, three males, including this one,
# 有3條公豬 其它全是母的
three males. Others are all females.
# 小豬
Piggy!
# 你不怕我啦
Aren't you afraid of me?
# 你看 它們那 那兩條小狗也喝 也喻了一點酒糟哦
Look! They, the puppies have also drunk, have also eaten some distillers grains.
# 它們兩個在幹架啦
And they're having a fight now.
# 咬它 看誰厲害一點
Bite it! See who is stronger!
# 就這樣被 就被它們吃完啦
And so, so they have finished the distillers grains.
# 你看 這個
Look! It,
# 好像暈暈的 它找地方睡覺啦
it seems to be a bit dizzy. It's finding a place to sleep.
# 一說它 它就轉過來看我 是不是
It turns to stare at me once I talk about it. Am I right?
# 暈不暈
Do you feel dizzy?
# 還那麼靈活
It's still so agile.
# 就沒暈
So it's not dizzy at all.
# 知道 給它多吃一點
I should have let it eat more.
# 來呀來呀來呀 來呀 來呀 呵呵
Go, go go! Yeah! Yeah! Ho ho!
# 還能爬得上去喲 可以喲
It can still climb up there, not bad!
# 你看 它們吃得 全部吃得肚子都圓圓的啦
Look! They've all eaten so much that their bellies are all round.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.